Guide to the Rainbow Triangle Oral History Collection UA.29.03.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rainbow Triangle Oral History Collection
1997-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for LGBT Life
UA.29.03.0001
4 Linear Feet
The Rainbow Triangle Oral History Project was originally conceived in 1996 as a way to document the lives of LGBT (Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender) people in the Triangle region in particular and central North Carolina in general. Ian Lekus became the Project Coordinator in 1996 and worked with a varying group of volunteers to acquire resources, conduct interviews, and ensure the preservation and access of the oral histories collected. More than 60 interviews were conducted between 1999 and 2004. The Rainbow Triangle Oral History Collection includes original oral history recordings, transcripts, biographical information on narrators, newsclippings, correspondence, and research materials.
Biographical / Historical
The Rainbow Triangle Oral History Project was originally conceived in 1996, by then-Director of Duke's Center for Lesbian, Gay & Bisexual Life (later the Center for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Life, now the Center for Sexual and Gender Diversity) John Howard, who suggested the project to Ian Lekus, then a Ph.D. candidate in the Department of History and a member of the Duke University Task Force for Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Matters.
The project was envisioned as a way to document the lives of LGBT people in the Triangle region in particular and central North Carolina in general, with the additional goals of exploring the idea of community identities and formation, breaking down barriers between the University and the local community, and documenting the HIV/AIDS epidemic in the Triangle.
Lekus became the Project Coordinator in 1996 and worked with a varying group of volunteers to acquire resources, conduct interviews, and ensure the preservation and access of the oral histories collected. From 1996 to late 1997, Lekus worked with others at Duke and elsewhere to develop forms and processes, conduct training workshops for interviewers, and establish how interviewes would be used and preserved. Anne Valk, a visiting professor at Duke, and Patrick Toal and Parker Doig, graduate students at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, were other active project leaders at this time. In February 1998, the project was officially launched during a talk by author and activist Mab Segrest on the Duke campus, but the first group of interviews were conducted in late 1998 and early 1999.
Dr. Karen Krahulik became the Director of the Center for LGBT Life in 1999 and continued support for the project. In Fall 2000, Dr. Krahulik and Ian Lekus co-taught a class called American Communities: Gender, Sexuality, and Oral History, presented by the Women's Studies Program and the History Department, and sponsored by the Center for Documentary Studies. As part of this class, students conducted oral history interviews that focused on gender and sexuality in the lives of the narrators, and several of these interviews were conducted as part of the Rainbow Triangle project. Ian Lekus taught this class again in 2004, and additional interviews from this class became part of the project.
Narrators are generally residents of the Triangle region, many of them with a connection to Duke or Durham in particular. Narrators include both LGBT people and heterosexual people who have been involved in LGBT issues in some way. Interviewers include Duke staff or volunteers for the Center for LGBT Life, Duke students, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill students, and others.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Portions of this collection are restricted by the request of the donor or narrator of an interview.
Portions of this collection are restricted due to the absence of a release form from the persons interviewed.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Rainbow Triangle Oral Histories were received as a gift in 2003, 2006, and 2016.
Scope and Contents
The Rainbow Triangle Oral History Collection includes original oral history recordings, transcripts, biographical information on narrators, newsclippings, correspondence, and research materials. Oral history interviews are primarily sound recordings, covering a wide range of topics including the narrators' early lives, families and family relationships, education, social life, experience of their own sexual identity, experience in or work with the LGBT community (in the Triangle and elsewhere), activism, working lives, romantic partners, professional activities, and many other topics. Original recordings are primarily on audiocassette tapes. About half of the oral histories also include printed transcripts. A few oral histories also include additional biographical information about the narrator, much of it included on an information sheet created by the Rainbow Triangle project, but sometimes also including additional material such as news articles, correspondence, flyers, and other items. Also included are materials related to the planning and development of the project, including correspondence, drafts, notes, and background research into LGBT life in the Triangle and oral history as a documentary form, as well as several years worth of the Pink Triangle issue of the local Independent Weekly.
Related Materials
Alliance of Queer Undergraduates at Duke (AQUADuke) Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Task Force records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Catherine Nicholson Papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: Oral Histories, Project Materials, and Newspapers.
Oral history interviews; Gay college teachers -- United States; Gay activists -- North Carolina; Gay bars; Gay community -- North Carolina; Gay parents; Gay couples -- North Carolina; Lesbian community -- North Carolina; Lesbians -- Health and hygiene; Lesbian mothers; Lesbian feminism; Lesbian couples -- North Carolina; Lesbian couples as parents; Gender identity -- United States; Sexual minorities -- North Carolina; Coming out (sexual orientation) -- United States; Duke University. Center for LGBT Life; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; Allen, Calvin; Ramiro, Arceo; Armentrout, Michael; Austin, Paula; Beam, Jeffrey; Brantley, Bill, -2002; Butters, Ron; Cameron, Danny; Chatman, Carliss; Childers, Lloyd; Clay, Anthony; Cruickshank-Schott, Patti; Edmund, Sophie; Dennis Eileen, Sister; Floyd, Wanda; Friedman, Riki; Giles, Donna Lee; Gilkeson, William R.; Goodman, Galia; Herndon, Godfrey; Herzenberg, Joseph A., 1941-; Johnson, Kristina M.; Johnson, Tony; Kaplan, Roger; Kast, Charles; Kinlaw, Sherry; Levine, Kenny; Linde, Maddy; LoBiondo, Deborah; Lohse, David; Long, Sharon; Mason, Jo Ellen; McCort, Agnieszka; McLenaghan, Natalie; Mills, Chadwick; Moore, Irv; Morgan, Leigh; Nicholson, Catherine; Padamsee, Xiomara; Palmquist, Ian; Perrier, Erica; Pham, Milan; Raines, Sara-Jane; Rosario, Jessica; Rudy, Kathy; Rutherford, Carlton; Sherratt, Thomas; Sherwood, Amie; Smiley, Erica; Taylor, Doris A.; Teasley, Alan B.; Tino, Michael; Tobin, Leslie; Unks, Gerald; Vicci, Leandra; Walker, Joan; Walton, April; Watson, Marki
- Oral histories, 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes original recordings of oral history interviews with narrators in the Rainbow Triangle Project. The majority of recordings are on audiocassette tapes, with a few video recordings on tapes. About half of the interviews include a printed transcript, some of which are incomplete; these transcripts were generally created by the interviewer. Many interviews also include completed biographical information sheets, created by the Project and completed by the narrator around the time of the interview. These forms may include information on the narrator's early life, education, work, civic activities, and other biographical topics. Some files also include additional materials, including correspondence, news articles, flyers, and publications. Many of these interviews were conducted by Duke students as part of the Duke undergraduate class American Communities: Gender, Sexuality, and Oral History in 2000 and 2004; two of the files include papers written by the student interviewers about the narrators with whom they worked.
  - Allen, Calvin, 1
    Biographical / Historical
    Administrator in nonprofit sector focusing on rural economic development; graduate of Duke, class of 1992. Originally from North Carolina.
    - Calvin Allen interview (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0001)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Interview restricted due to lack of signed release form from the interviewee.
  - Arceo, Ramiro, 2
    Staff member at Student Action with Farmworkers, originally from Colima, Mexico.
    - Ramiro Arceo interview, April 22, 2003 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0002)
    - Ramiro Arceo transcript, email, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Armentrout, Michael, 3
    Owner of MEA Financial Services and graduate of Duke, class of 1978, originally from West Virginia. As of 2016, president of the Nicholas Sparks Foundation.
    - Michael Armentrout interview Tape 1, April 25, 1999 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0003)
      Use restrictions apply.
    - Michael Armentrout interview Tape 2, April 25, 1999 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0004)
    - Michael Armentrout transcript, transcript draft, biographical information sheet, articles, 1999-2001 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Austin, Paula, 4
    Executive Director of North Carolina Lambda Youth Network and graduate student of history at North Carolina Central University (NCCU), originally from Georgetown, Guyana.
    - Paula Austin interview, 2000 November 17 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0005)
    - Paula Austin transcript, biographical information sheet, article, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Beam, Jeffrey, 5
    Poet and library assistant, graduate of UNC-CH, class of 1975. Originally from Kannapolis, North Carolina.
    - Jeffrey Scott Beam interview, 1999 June 28 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0006)
    - Jeffrey Scott Beam biographical information sheet, correspondence, writings, photographs, 1977-1998, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Jeffrey Beam photographs, 1991-1992 (Oversize-folder 1)
      Art photographs (nudes).
  - Brantley, Bill, 6
    AIDS activist and former newspaper reporter, editor, and executive. Originally from North Carolina. Died July 14, 2002.
    - Bill Brantley interview, October 12, 1998 (Box 9, Video-cassette UA29030001-Hi8-0001)
    - Bill Brantley interview (Box 9, Video-cassette UA29030001-VHS-0001)
    - Bill Brantley news article, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Butters, Ronald, 7
    English professor at Duke University, originally from Cedar Rapids, Iowa.
    - Ronald Butters interview Tape 1, 2000 November 22 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0007)
    - Ronald Butters interview Tape 2, 2000 November 22 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0008)
    - Ronald Butters transcript, biographical information sheet, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Cameron, Danny, 8
    Owner of Cameron's shop in University Mall, Chapel Hill; graduate of UNC-CH, class of 1973. Originally from Wilmington, North Carolina.
    - Danny Cameron interview Tape 1, 2000 December 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0009)
    - Danny Cameron interview Tape 2, 2000 December 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0010)
    - Danny Cameron transcript, biographical information sheet, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chatman, Carliss, 9
    Staff member at Women's Center of Duke University, graduate of Duke, class of 2001. Originally from Houston, Texas.
    - Carliss Chatman interview, March 21, 2001 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0011)
    - Carliss Chatman biographical information sheet, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Childers, Lloyd, 10
    Lighthouse keeper and Executive Director of Outer Banks Conservationists; graduate of UNC-CH, class of 1958; graduate of NC State, 1984. As of 2016, watercolor and print artist. Originally from Montclair, New Jersey.
    - Lloyd Childers interview, November 2, 1998 (Box 9, Video-cassette UA29030001-Hi8-0002)
    - Lloyd Childers biographical information sheet, pamphlets, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Clay, Anthony, 11
    High school and elementary school teacher, originally from Arkansas.
    - Anthony L. Clay interview (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0012)
  - Cruickshank-Schott, Patti, 12
    Teacher, activist in LGBT community. Originally from western Massachussetts.
    - Patti Cruickshank-Schott interview Tape 1, 2000 November 19 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0013)
    - Patti Cruickshank-Schott interview Tape 2, 2000 November 19 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0014)
    - Patti Cruickshank-Schott transcript (incomplete), 2000 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Dennis Eileen, Sr., 14
    Roman Catholic nun (Sisters of Saint Joseph), teacher, active in AIDS ministry and ministry to gay community. Originally from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Died December 31, 2010.
    - Sr. Dennis Eileen transcript, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Edmund, Sophie, 13
    No biographical information available.
    - Sophie Edmund interview (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0015)
    - Sophie Edmund transcript, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Floyd, Wanda, 15
    Reverend and founding pastor of Imani Metropolitan Community Church (Imani MCC) in Durham; graduate of NC State, class of 1987. Originally from Henderson, North Carolina.
    - Wanda Floyd Tape 1 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0016)
    - Wanda Floyd Tape 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0017)
    - Wanda Floyd biographical information sheet, articles, 1991, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Issue of Independent Weekly featuring Wanda Floyd, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Friedman, Riki, 16
    Activist for women's health issues, especially those of lesbians; member of klezmer band Freylach Time!. Originally from Long Beach, California.
    - Riki Friedman interview Tape 1 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0018)
    - Riki Friedman interview Tape 2 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0019)
    - Riki Friedman interview Tape 3 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0020)
    - Riki Friedman interview Tape 4 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0021)
    - Riki Friedman interview Tape 5 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0022)
    - Riki Friedman transcript, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Giles, Donna Lee, 17
    Staff member in the Duke Graduate School Admissions Office, founding member of the LGB Task Force, and graduate of Duke, class of 1969. Originally from Danville, Virginia.
    - Donna Giles interview Tape 1 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0023)
    - Donna Giles interview Tape 2 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0024)
    - Donna Giles transcript, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Gilkeson, Bill, 18
    Member of the legal staff of the North Carolina General Assembly; graduate of UNC-Chapel Hill Law School, 1985. Originally from Tennessee.
    - Bill Gilkeson interview Tape 1, March 22, 2000 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0025)
      Release form is not signed.
    - Bill Gilkeson interview Tape 2, March 22, 2000 and May 17, 2000 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0026)
    - Bill Gilkeson interview Tape 3, May 17, 2000 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0027)
    - Bill Gilkeson interview Tape 4 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0028)
  - Goodman, Galia, 19
    Papercutting and calligraphy artist, originally from Denver, Colorado.
    - Galia Goodman interview (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0029)
    - Galia Goodman transcript, biographical information sheet, Voices magazine, brochure, 1999, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Herndon, Godfrey, 20
    Member of the Board of Directors of the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project, based in Durham, North Carolina.
    - Godfrey Herndon interview Tape 1, October 10, 2000 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0030)
    - Godfrey Herndon interview Tape 2, October 10, 2000 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0031)
  - Herzenberg, Joe, 21
    Historian and activist for social, economic, and environmental causes; the first openly gay elected official in North Carolina (Chapel Hill Town Council, 1987); UNC-CH graduate work in history 1969-1981. Originally from Franklin, New Jersey. Born 1941, died October 28, 2007.
    - Joe Herzenberg interview Tape 1, March 1, 1999 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0032)
    - Joe Herzenberg interview Tape 2, March 1, 1999 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0033)
    - Joe Herzenberg interview Tape 3, March 1, 1999 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0034)
    - Joe Herzenberg biographical information sheet, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "Jay, Jodie", 22
    This interviewee elected to use a pseudonym.
    Singer, songwriter, and musician and manager of a law firm. Originally from Florence, South Carolina.
    - Jodie Jay interview (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0035)
    - Jodie Jay transcript, paper by Ryan White (interviewer), 2003 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Johnson, Kristina, 23
    Dean of the Pratt School of Engineering and former college athlete. Originally from St. Louis, Missouri.
    - [Kristina Johnson Interview] Tape 1 (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29030001-MCS-0001)
    - [Kristina Johnson Interview] Tape 2 (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29030001-MCS-0002)
    - Kristina Johnson transcript, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Johnson, Tony, 24
    Dancer and choreographer, activist and minister to people with HIV/AIDS.
    - Tony Johnson interview (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0036)
    - Tony Johnson transcript, biographical information sheet, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Tony Johnson news article, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Kaplan, Roger, 25
    Former director of the Freeman Center for Jewish Life and father of adopted son. Originally from southern California; resident of Durham at the time of the interview.
    - Roger Kaplan interview Tape 1, April 24, 2003 (Box 2, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0037)
    - Roger Kaplan interview Tape 2, April 24, 2003 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0038)
    - Roger Kaplan transcript, biographical information sheet, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Kast, Charles, 26
    Unitarian Universalist minister based in Chapel Hill; single foster parent to 85 boys between 1985 and 1999. Originally from Massachusetts.
    - Charles Kast interview Tape 1 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0037)
    - Charles Kast interview Tape 2 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0038)
    - Charles Kast biographical information sheet, correspondence, article, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Kinlaw, Sherry, 27
    Owner of Francesca's Dessert Caffe in Durham, North Carolina. Originally from Lumberton, North Carolina.
    - Sherry Kinlaw interview Tape 1 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0039)
    - Sherry Kinlaw interview Tape 2 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0040)
    - Sherry Kinlaw transcript, biographical information sheet, articles, photographs, 1999-2001 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Levine, Kenny, 28
    Licensed Clinical Social Worker based in Durham, North Carolina.
    - Kenny Levine interview (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0043)
  - Linde, Maddy, 29
    - Maddy Linde interview, April 20, 2004 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0044)
  - LoBiondo, Deborah, 30
    Administrator in Duke Student Affairs. Originally from New Jersey.
    - Deborah LoBiondo interview, April 24, 2003 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0045)
    - Deborah LoBiondo transcript, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lohse, Dave, 31
    Director in Sports Information at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Originally from the Chicago area.
    - Dave Lohse interview Tape 1, November 29, 2000 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0046)
    - Dave Lohse interview Tape 2, November 29, 2000 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0047)
    - Dave Lohse transcript, biographical information sheet, articles, 2000-2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Long, Sharon, 32
    Greensboro-based professional, active in the Imani Metropolitan Community Church of Durham. Originally from Trinidad.
    - Sharon Long interview, 2003 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0048)
    - Sharon Long transcript, biographical information sheet, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mason, Jo Ellen, 33
    Realtor and nurse based in Durham, North Carolina. Originally from Texas.
    - Jo Ellen Mason interview Tape 1, September 7, 2000 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0049)
    - Jo Ellen Mason interview Tape 2, September 7, 2000 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0050)
    - Jo Ellen Mason biographical information sheet, postcards, 2000 (Box 7)
  - McCort, Agnieszka, 34
    Youth Prevention Coordinator at the Durham Crisis Response Center at the time of interview.
    - Agnieszka McCort interview, April 9, 2004 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0051)
  - McLenaghan, Natalie, 35
    Proprietor of the Cafe at the Regulator (Durham, North Carolina) at the time of interview.
    - Natalie McLenaghan interview Tape 1, April 23, 2004 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0052)
    - Natalie McLenaghan interview Tape 2, April 23, 2004 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0053)
    - Natalie McLenaghan interview Tape 3, April 23, 2004 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0054)
  - Mills, Chadwick, 36
    - Chadwick Mills interview, February 28, 2001 (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0055)
    - Chadwick Mills interview, undated (Box 3, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0056)
    - Chadwick Mills biographical information sheet, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Moore, Irv, 37
    Chaplain at Duke Hospital. Originally from Burlington, North Carolina.
    - Irv Moore interview, October 20, 1998 (Box 4, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0057)
      Interview restricted. Contact Research Services for more information.
    - Irv Moore biographical information sheet, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Morgan, Leigh, 38
    Graduate of Duke (1990) who was starting point guard on the women's basketball team.
    - Leigh Morgan interview, April 22, 2004 (Box 4, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0058)
  - Nicholson, Catherine, 39
    Theater director/producer; co-founder and editor of the journal Sinister Wisdom. Born 1922, died 2013.
    - Catherine Nicholson interview Tape 1 (Box 4, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0059)
    - Catherine Nicholson interview Tape 2 (Box 4, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0060)
  - Padamsee, Xiomara, 40
    Assistant Coordinator of the Sexual Assault Support Services (SASS) at Duke University.
    - Xiomara Padamsee interview Tape 1 (Box 4, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0061)
    - Xiomara Padamsee interview Tape 2 (Box 4, Audio-cassette UA29030001-CS-0062)
  - Palmquist, Ian, 41